<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="jfinocchiar.girhub.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="jfinocchiar.girhub.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-12T12:07:19+00:00</updated><id>jfinocchiar.girhub.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jessie Finocchiaro</title><subtitle>Homepage for Jessie Finocchiaro </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Unsolicited advice on graduate applications</title><link href="jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2021/gradapps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unsolicited advice on graduate applications"/><published>2021-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2021/gradapps</id><content type="html" xml:base="jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2021/gradapps/"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few years, I’ve been fortunate enough to talk to prospective students through Open House weekends, structured mentoring opportunities, and the occasional cold email. (Totally cool to <a href="mailto:jessie@seas.harvard.edu">email me</a>; if we’re not acquainted, please include “Marshfield” in the subject line.)</p> <p>Through these interactions, I’m constantly reminded about:</p> <ul> <li>My curse of knowledge about how graduate school operates.</li> <li>How much I do not miss applying to graduate programs.</li> </ul> <p>With that, and it being graduate application season, I figured I would offer some unsolicited suggestions for applying to graduate programs. (For context: I am an American student at an American university, so I am not as familiar with the visa process, TOEFL, or any of the other ridiculous hoops my international friends often have to jump through.) Also, here is a <a href="https://twitter.com/jessie_fin/status/1201719502934667265?s=20">twitter thread</a> to some advice from the Twitterverse in case you want to hear others’ opinions!</p> <h3 id="resources-from-others">Resources from others!</h3> <ul> <li>Chinasa T. Okolo has some great resources including this list of <a href="https://github.com/chinasaokolo/csGraduateApps">CS programs with graduate application fee waivers</a> and this list of <a href="https://github.com/chinasaokolo/csWorkshops">CS workshops</a>.</li> <li>Andrew Kuznetsov had a <a href="http://www.andrewkuz.net/cs-hci-research-hub/">great list</a> of questions to ask potential advisors, their group, and your potential department.</li> </ul> <h3 id="writing-personal-statements">Writing personal statements</h3> <p>This is basically the only opportunity in most applications to share who you are. Most conversations I have had with application reviewers (faculty and staff) about personal statements have led me to believe that it is pretty easy to tell if someone didn’t actually write their own personal statement.</p> <p>In grad school, I’ve learned how helpful the art of storytelling is, even in scientific writing. Passion in one’s writing is almost contagious; when authors are excited about their research, it makes their papers more fun to read. The personal statement is the opportunity to share your passion and excitement about science. The reviewer already has your CV, so I would be wary of simply listing your credentials. Instead, think about telling the story and bringing life to your CV.</p> <h3 id="for-example">For example…</h3> <p>When I started graduate school, I completely switched research areas. My undergraduate research projects ranged from designing machine learning (ML) algorithms for computer vision problems to using genetic algorithms to simulate a multi-agent setting to investigate how to incentivize cooperation in a group.</p> <p>In my interviews, I generally presented myself as a robotics or computer vision candidate, mostly because I didn’t know what I wanted to do. It wasn’t until later that I realized that I was more intrigued about learning <em>how</em> our machine learning algorithm was making predictions than I was about <em>what</em> decisions were made. This curiosity eventually steered me towards theoretical ML, where I currently do my work. I felt like an imposter (and often still do) when I first started in theory because I was learning everything from scratch. However, because I was able to articulate my desire in understanding the processes underlying ML in my personal statement, one of the faculty I interviewed with ended up suggesting I take the leap into theory because he could tell it was where I would be more successful because of that curiosity and passion.</p> <h3 id="interviews">Interviews</h3> <p>This is probably generally for domestic applicants, although I have occasionally met an international student or two who have been able to travel for interviews. I will preface this with the note that every school (and degree program) is different. I applied to 6 graduate programs and got invited for 5 interviews, but only 3 of those programs had a formal Open House recruitment weekend while the other two offered to pay for me to take an individual visit for a weekend.</p> <p>Before the Open House “interview”, some faculty will set up video calls for interviews to pre-screen prospective students. Within my department at least, this is not uniform, but varies from lab to lab and faculty to faculty. The point of these phone calls is almost never a technical vetting, but they typically aim to figure out if there is a personality and work fit between the prospective student and advisor pair.</p> <p>At most larger universities, it seems to be the norm that programs will have an Open House weekend in February-March, where they invite some prospective students to visit the campus for a weekend. At some universities, you may receive an admission offer before the visit, and others may not give out offers until after.</p> <p>For these weekends, the university will typically put you up in a hotel (I have heard of prospective students staying on a current student’s couch, though, too) and reimburse you for flights. The reason for reimbursing flights, at least in my conversations and experience, is the burden of rescheduling flights if the university books them and a winter storm rolls in to change plans. <em>If being reimbursed for the flight is not gonna financially work for you, reach out to the department. It sucks to have to do, but they may be able to help in individual situations.</em> They almost definitely will understand, especially since they know people will have to pay for flights to go to multiple universities. After you paid upwards of $1000 on applications, to drop another grand waiting to be reimbursed is a lot to ask, and people understand that. And if the university doesn’t sympathize with that, it’s probably a program you don’t want to be in.</p> <h3 id="overall-thoughts-on-grad-school">Overall thoughts on grad school</h3> <p>I love my job, and I’m so fortunate to be in my current situation. That being said, I also know that the life I live is one of incredible privilege. For those who are caretakers for loved ones, being able to take a pay cut for 5-6 years may not be a luxury they can afford. I often find myself in awe that I get paid to learn and contribute to the scientific community. However, if the narrative of science is only written by the privileged, we won’t get nearly as far as we could if we had an inclusive community. So I hope this encourages any readers who’ve made it this far to put yourself out there, and find your spot in the community where you feel welcomed at the table.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academic"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with custom blockquotes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NSF GRFP Example</title><link href="jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2020/grfp_blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NSF GRFP Example"/><published>2020-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2020/grfp_blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2020/grfp_blog/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p><a href="../files/researchplan_grfp.pdf">Here</a> is my research statement that I submitted for the NSF GRFP. Personal statements and reviews are available <a href="mailto:jessie@seas.harvard.edu">upon request</a> as well. Please note that the formatting requirements have changed over time, so please check them carefully.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academic"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Example materials from the NSF GRFP]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in Academia</title><link href="jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2019/dei_blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in Academia"/><published>2019-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2019/dei_blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="jfinocchiar.girhub.io/blog/2019/dei_blog/"><![CDATA[<p> Preface: I have never sat on an admissions committee, and my thoughts are based on conversations I have been able to observe, mostly on Twitter. These aren't necessarily representative of my department, and I can't speak to any specific university. This is a compilation of overarching themes I've observed from a variety of (primarily USA-based) academics. My thoughts are obviously going to be skewed by who I do (and, more importantly, don't) know. </p> <hr/> <p><strong>Diversity and Inclusion</strong>. It’s almost as much of a buzzword in Comp Sci as “Machine Learning” right now. Personally, I tend to lump the two together without parsing them as two separate concepts most of the time, so I’d like to take a second to break the two up.</p> <p><strong>Diversity</strong>: Who is in the room? Do the experiences that people bring to a project represent all backgrounds? Notably, are there people (and not just one “token person”) who have the life experience and perspective.</p> <p>A soccer metaphor: You don’t want a soccer team full of forwards. You need some midfielders, defenders, and goalkeepers. A roster of 11 forwards won’t ever win a game.</p> <p><strong>Inclusion</strong>: Once a “diverse” group of people are part of your cohort, are they part of your community? Do they feel safe to voice their opinions?</p> <p>Soccer metaphor continued: So you have a balanced roster of forwards, midfielders, defenders, and goalies. First, you need to practice together so you can work as a team. But more than that, by working with forwards, defenders and goalies can learn what to look for when facing an opposing forward, so that when it’s game time, they’re prepared for the challenges ahead.</p> <h3 id="features-are-not-equal-to-experiences">Features are not equal to experiences</h3> <p>There are a plethora of experiences I have had as a woman in Computer Science, both positive and negative. I’ve bonded with labmates as self-proclaimed “bad-ass women of science.” I’ve been (to my knowledge) the only woman in the room as a professor told our class to “never get married, because women just take your money and ruin your lives.” These experiences shape who I am, and I am able to relate to many other women through these experiences.</p> <p>Because I check the “woman” box, it is assumed I bring that family of experiences to the table, and this is the diversity I bring. Because we have an obsession with quantification, we tend to represent people– and their human experiences– as this vector of characteristics, in a sense.</p> <p>Diversity stems from experiences, not from features. Often, our experiences are shaped by our features, but they are not solely our features.</p> <h3 id="our-obsession-with-quantification">Our obsession with quantification</h3> <p>The first step in solving a problem is acknowledging it exists. To a large extent, Computer Scientists in the United States recognize that the ~80$\%$ male-identifying population of computer scientists in the US is not representative of the ~50$\%$ population of male-identifying people in both the US and world. And this is a great first step.</p> <p>As companies and university departments push to “be diverse,” whatever that means, we want to quantify <em>how diverse</em> we are: “Half of our students are female.” “10$\%$ of our team self-identifies as queer.” “20$\%$ of our students are people of color.” It goes on.</p> <p>I have three knee-jerk issues here:</p> <ul> <li>We can’t really quantify inclusion that well, and quantifying our diversity only gets us so far.</li> <li>This reduces peoples’ human experiences to the labels we slap on them.</li> <li>If we do accept considering people as a collection of features, we tend to miss many unique experiences that are correlated with the intersectionality of these labels.</li> </ul> <p>In our diversity-hacking, we tend to ignore the intersectionality of many of the labels we slap onto people. For example, a 1976 <a href="https://openjurist.org/558/f2d/480/emma-degraffenreid-et-al-v-general-motors-assembly-division-st-louis">lawsuit</a> against General Motors Corporation, led by Emma DeGraffenreid and other former GM employers alleged employment discrimination in the workplace. In GM’s defense, they claimed that they had both black employees and female employees, so they clearly did not discriminate. However, looking at the intersectionality of these labels, the company had disproportionately few black women hired at GM at the time. (Yes, this was 1976, but this is one of the more famous examples on the importance of intersectionality. Modern examples can certainly be found as well.)</p> <p>When we solely aim to “be diverse,” we try to choose how to measure diversity in the lowest-cost, lowest-impact way possible. This gives companies and universities an easy out. <strong>As a result, Diversity and Inclusion initiatives in tech often disproportionately benefit white women of higher socioeconomic status.</strong> See <a href="https://www.vox.com/2016/12/20/14013610/gender-diversity-women-race-age-geography-initiative">this article</a> for some examples of people who get neglected by the convenience of focusing on the most convenient “minority group” in tech.</p> <p>Now don’t get me wrong. Being able to set quantifiable goals for oneself is generally a good thing. Not all quantification of D&amp;I initiatives is bad, but I remain critical of clinging to them for dear life.</p> <h3 id="how-academia-discriminates-a-very-incomplete-list">How academia discriminates (a very incomplete list)</h3> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Barrier to entry</strong>: As one example, parents (especially single parents) are often discouraged from entering academia because of the possible pay cut as a graduate student, sometimes excessive hours expected, and struggle to find childcare when conference travel is required.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Selection process</strong>: When admissions decisions are filtered down based on a resume, it doesn’t encapsulate potential; it captures (utilization of) past opportunity. We’re missing a part of the admission pipeline that shows potential and interest. Instead, we incentivize “accomplishing diversity” in the cheapest and most convenient way possible.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="other-resources">Other resources</h3> <ul> <li><a href="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/~bindel/paper/diversity.pdf">David Bindel’s summary of Cornell’s efforts.</a></li> <li><a href="https://ainowinstitute.org/discriminatingsystems.pdf">AINow Institute’s work on discrimination in AI</a></li> </ul> <h3 id="an-aside-some-of-the-experience-i-bring-to-the-table-here">An aside: some of the experience I bring to the table here</h3> <p>In my personal experience, I grew up in a town where many people return after college, if they go. A four-year university experience wasn’t expected of us like I have been able to see in my past life as a youth pastor just outside Washington, D.C. I started at my liberal-arts college as a math major because 1. we didn’t have engineering and 2. it was the only subject in high school that I continually found intriguing. We didn’t have any Computer Science classes at my high school. My parents don’t work anywhere near tech. When I started undergrad, I picked the cheapest school possible in state because my parents said they would pay for my graduate degree out of state (this speaks wonders to my financial privilege that my parents would have been able to help me out in that way) if I stayed in Florida for undergrad. I took my first Comp Sci class because it was required for the math major. I thought I was terrible at programming (which at the time, I equated to Computer Science) because I had never programmed before. After a month or so, I promised myself I would never take another CS class. In large part, this was because I felt alone in the class; I was the only woman. It seemed like everyone else knew what they were doing when I was lost. Thankfully, I found a wonderful advisor who encouraged me to apply to graduate programs after seeing how much I enjoyed research, but only after two years of avoiding the subject entirely. Mentorship from my undergraduate advisor is the only reason I’ve survived in the field</p> <p>In the two years I spent avoiding computing entirely, I was able to do two internships as a youth pastor: one just outside D.C. in a predominantly wealthy suburb, and one in a rural North Carolina town. My students in D.C. seemed to be expected to do x, y, and z to boost their resumes to get into top universities. I honestly got burnt out just observing them for a summer. In North Carolina, it was a big deal when students went to a four-year university. Tech wasn’t particularly emphasized, since there weren’t any major tech companies in the area. People seemed to get jobs or degrees they were familiar with. In most cases, these young people weren’t shown that careers in tech were a viable option. <em>By and large, they didn’t have the role models to show them a path to tech.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academic"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Unsolicited thoughts on why we should care about fostering a diverse and inclusive environment in the workplace]]></summary></entry></feed>